Guide to the Lida Moser Photograph Collection 1971, 1978 PR 123
New-York Historical Society
Lida Moser Photograph Collection
1971, 1978
New-York Historical Society
PR 123
0.92 Linear feet (1 box)
Photographs, taken by Lida Moser, documenting the Washington Market area of Lower Manhattan in 1971 and 1978.
Provenance
Purchased from the photographer, 2002.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
After working in a motion picture studio, doing camera work, sound and film editing, Lida Moser was convinced by a colleague to try still photography. She immediately took to it, enjoying the total control she had over the process.
In 1947, Moser became an assistant in Berenice Abbott's studio, helping to organize a collection of Eugene Atget prints and negatives. After leaving Abbott's studio, Moser photographed for various magazines including Vogue, Harper's Bazaar, and Look. She worked as staff photographer for Playwright's Inc., a Broadway theatre production company, for two years. She worked with realist painter John Koch, photographing him, his work, exhibits and events, from 1954 to 1974. She also wrote several books on photography, created images for book cover art, and worked as photojournalist in several countries, taking photographs for over 60 years.
Scope and Content Note
The Lida Moser Photograph Collection contains thirteen gelatin silver photographic prints, taken in 1971 and 1978 of the former Washington Market area of lower Manhattan, prior to and during the construction of the World Trade Center.
Photographs include views of demolition sites, individual streets, tenements and commercial buildings in the Washington Market district that were affected or demolished during the course of construction. A number of images include views of Greenwich, Washington, Harrison, and other streets, with the World Trade Center towers in various stages of construction in the background. Also included is a single photograph taken by Moser in 1978 from the top of the World Trade Center towers, facing northeast towards Brooklyn and Long Island.
Arrangement
Lida Moser assigned each photograph a number, which corresponded to a negative in her collection. The photographs are arranged by these assigned numbers.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional images of the area can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020) and the Subway Construction Photograph Collection (PR 069).
Gelatin silver prints.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Women photographers.; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001) -- Design and construction -- Photographs.
- Series I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Photographs are arranged by their negative numbers, listed in parentheses, which were assigned by the photographer. Descriptions, in brackets, were given by N-YHS staff.
  - [Looking S.W. from 360 Greenwich Street] (574-1-0), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - [On Roof of 360 Greenwich Street, looking North] (574-1-1), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Bell Telephone Building, On Vesey Street] (574-1-17), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Washington and Harrison Streets, looking S.E.] (574-1-26), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - [From Washington Street] (574-1-28), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Sixty Greenwich Street looking S.W.] (574-3-11), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - [From Roof of 360 Greenwich Street, looking S.E.] (574-4-1), 3 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Washington Street looking East] (574-5-16), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Tenement Building, 360 Greenwich Street] (574-5-25), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Corner of Franklin and Greenwich Streets, looking South] (574-6-2), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - [North Moore and Greenwich Streets, looking North] (574-6-4), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Looking South from North Moore Street] (574-6-5), 28 March 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - [View from top of Twin Towers, looking N.E.] (893-3), July 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)